I will call it one of the most specials.
You tell the authority more meeting for one, three, and 22 of them, two invocations by
Director of Norse Campus Ministries and Mr. Steve Watson.
I have to figure a couple of times a year, I always like to bring you good news for
many of our athletics.
If you've not seen any of our teams participate in their sports, I encourage you to do so
basketball and wrestling work came back today to the finest problems in the nation.
You can go to NEO, athletics.com to see what the schedule is.
I encourage you to get involved.
We have students in our athletic programs from 16 different countries around the world, right here
in the middle of the home.
I was interested in seeing a kid come in here from home, or give us law here, or whatever
they're right here in our community.
Our fellow super Christian athletes, Bible study, weekly Bible study with all our teams, average
to 160 students this fall, that's a record for us.
We just completed our capital campaign for funding this program, this week, we raised $60,000,
very little of it, can't from town, it can't from alumni across the nation, and so we're just,
I'm here to brag just a little bit tonight and say things are more and more within the
away place.
This program.
Father, thank you for this time and we can come and conduct our city business, we thank
you for our partner, major research, all the people men and women at the city of Miami,
all the blessiness and make decisions with all of our lives, we thank you for this community,
we thank you for my home too, probably just bless this meeting tonight.
And then, I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America and to the
Republic for which it's saying one nation and another guy who did a visit with a letter he needs
to ask us all.
I'm a former Republican, but I'm scheduled personal appearances, five, consent and agenda staff
recommends we approve of item six and seven.
Make the motion approved.
I'm sorry.
Parker.
All right.
So I'm full.
Hi.
I'm Steve.
Hello.
Is this part of the session.
Carmen?
Hello.
to the professional services where the legal claims are paid.
Again, not in the money, until the rest of the last few receipts, nice to be able to say it.
The promotion rate group?
Second.
Is that fine?
Davis?
All right.
Don't vote.
Five.
Perfect.
Thank you, Mike.
Now, in our local agreement between the city of Minamo and the Board of County
Commissioners of Water of County.
It's a bit of a question.
So this is an issue that goes back to some of the problems at the jail.
Back in the summer of last year, they had a very significant leak in their jail.
It took a long time to try to figure out what their problem was and to get it fixed.
But the upshot of it is we anticipate, or we, the calculations we did show that there was
about $30,000 of water and sewer that went through their system due to the leak.
For them to have paid that would have caused some further financial problems at the time the
sheriff's office could not adequately take care of.
So all of that to say that we've reached an agreement.
Paperwork was drawn up, probably about a month ago, but there were discussions between the
DA and myself as to whether we...
had to go through the Attorney General's Office to approve it, finally agreed with me that we
didn't have to, and so we are now presenting an agreement, where basically they're paying
us everything that they owe on the utility bills in total, that figure I want to give you
that figure again, it was 712. There you go. In the meantime, the county has the equipment
and manpower and expertise to do a demolition for us, that being the DFW building across the street,
and we reach an agreement that they will do that for the city at that same price. So we're
being paid in full, they will then do the demolition, and then we will pay them for that demolition.
The follow that makes sense. Is that demolition debris? Where is it going? Is it coming
to the city? Yes. It is, their demolition has to be done to the same standards that the
city does, but as part and parcel of this on any other demolition, but as part and parcel
of this, they have to get the, all of the permits, everything like they otherwise would,
that we are not charging them for that. So the debris cost is on them, or is this city absorbent
that? The city is absorbing that. And that is why this is coming, all this agreement entails utility
bill. So that's one of the reasons it's coming here, but also we're waving the tipping fee,
which is going through MSUA. Right. So that's the reason it's coming here, but it's also going on
our next meeting. Is there an estimated, well I guess what I'm saying is it's going to be more than
then $33,000. Is there an estimated tipping cost that is what it would cost the city to get rid of that?
It's on a tonnage basis. We kind of have an idea, but in essence we're paying them for the work.
We're not paying it. We're not paying it. We're not paying it. Right. Right. Not for the...
disposal of the debris. If we were to calculate it, that into it, then the expense of demolishing
the building would have been a lot more. When they get done, followed the debris, we'll be
all off from side. It'll be a finished grass surface just like we require on any other
demolition that is done. So I read in this thing that says when that's all set and down the city's
going to turn around and cut them a check for that amount. We're going to pay them for the demolition.
They're going to pay their water bill, and then we're going to turn and pay them for the work.
So they're going to pay us $71,000 and we're going to turn around and pay them $33,000, right?
Yes, because they owe us the $71,000 of that amount, $30,000 approximately is what we're in agreement
is attributable to the leak. Right, it's $30,000, $33,000, $30,000, $30,000. So they're going to take this
why about? Yes. They're taking it all the way down. So there's a basement. It mentions a basement in here,
is there a basement? Basically, it says they're going to take it all the way down below grade and refill it
in the top soil. Does there a basement, HT? No. No, it has to have top soil so that the grass can grow.
Is that smooth slab, raised slab, or what's underneath that? My information is that it's simply a slab,
so they have concrete slab, they have to pull that out, get it. Pull the footings out,
basically pull anything that's in there out and then re-grade it with top soil, a surface of top
soil so that we can grab that point. And if we determine at some point time that that lot will have been better
served as a parking lot, then we spend the money.
That's that is where we'd be at. Yes
We're doing straight all the way straight that we can go ramp to slabs now
So if the council desires to do it a different way we can we can do it although like I say
It's been a silver a month to get
Get to this point
We were gonna pay to have the VFW
Demolish no matter what I mean that was the
So did is there any other bands out there to know that their labor labor
Employment prices of fair price if you asked anybody else to bet
Yeah, I think we did look into getting other quotes so that we would know what it was gonna cost that's how we came up
The amount
For us to determine was there even anything that we mean so did you have someone else turn in a bit
Or give you a quote that signs we have
That's over there. I can't tell you exactly what's going to happen
May is it 9,000 or 10,000 I think it's a little
We're pretty nine and you think that here's one of the 11,000 that I can't
Just so that there's a full understanding I'd also point out that during the
month that the paperwork was over there
They went ahead and paid
$14,000 on
They're account
But in the meantime the December bill came due. It was actually due as of today
That was 8,719 dollars and 23 cents
So our figures
Well actually change a little bit. It'll be 65,0973 that they will pay us
But it's still
All and it provides in this agreement that it would be modified for the December payment
It's just that we actually know the figures now
There's an ask for about a basement if you looked at it close paragraph two
Section B says remove all floors foundations footings basement and retaining walls to a minimum of 18 inches
Blueprint. That's why I was asking you through the basement. I knew I'd read it. There's a mark. Yeah, that's generic. This is our standard language.
My own question.
I was just about consistency.
I took out a slab and I'm certainly thankful that I did at this point and then there was one left.
My daughter generally went to a ramp school.
Or they did.
Not knowing if at some point dynamic concerns as a parking lot of you should.
So generally what our rule of thumb is is if we have a plan for a location then we work with the owner of that to make sure that we're in line with that plan.
As I recall at the time that you did yours David, you didn't know what you wanted to do if you were going to sell it or build on it.
So you were wanting to leave it even though you might turn around and sell it.
And the history of my him on Main Street has been a problem. We end up with properties that have these partial slabs sitting on them that he values the property.
So anytime we can get it taken down to a consistent we want to do that.
We in dollar general approaches about theirs they had a plan of what they were going to do and build on it.
So we opted to work with the owner at the time so it makes keep their plan.
Now if they don't execute that to our acceptance then we need to think about what it is we're allowed to do.
Be more specific in the future about what we allow them to do.
As far as the V of W we don't know what we're going to do with it.
We might sell a lot. We might build on it.
We might turn it into a parking lot but this time we don't have a plan.
So in case we wanted to sell it or otherwise we wanted to put it back to grass.
And as far as the tradeoff and services go this is something that myself spoke with commissioner rose many times when this issue arose.
Tyler climbed to myself or on side of the jail trying to help find out at the time when this first happened.
They were using 75,000 gallons within like half a day of us getting over there to try to help figure out what was going on.
As I understand it they had multiple issues with their plumbing in the past and we were helping them look at their plumbing issues and finally Tyler and his crew was able to chase it down to some specific.
Commodes in the jail that were pretty high pressure commodes that were just running nonstop that had been busted.
And part of that is of course probably the individuals that we ourselves are putting in the jail that are helping to the destruction of this jail.
But we offered to work with them in a way that if there was something we could do to help
them, we would.
And this was detrimental to their budget and it's just a good community partner.
And someone that we have agreements with, say, for the use of the jail, we wanted to help them
with any way we could, knowing that they need to put all of their money back into rehabbing
the jail, not paying a water bill.
And since we looked internally and found that we had a need that was equivalent to the
same amount that we were going to be expending anyway and that was a service that they
could provide.
It seemed like a marriage made.
So we offered it up and been in the attorney's figure out how to make it happen.
And that's one lead us to this today.
But the idea was to, it was to help our county office in the best way that we could.
And this was something that was of no arm to the city, but was just a good steward of our service.
And there's, and we'd direct it then to that.
Thank you.
Much better.
Yes.
Davis?
Aye.
East.
No.
Ten.
The Joint Resolution 2022-01 of the Mayor and City Council of the City of Miami, Oklahoma,
and the Board of Trustees of the Minority Special Utility Authority Board for Community
Financial Support and Feedway of Work to the Mime Towers Housing Authority, and Mime
Towers Housing Authority and Nine Tribes Housing Authority for the remodels and renovations
of the Mime Towers and Nine Tribes Towers within the City of Mime of Oklahoma.
That was a mouthful.
It was.
Are you ready?
Yes.
I was waiting for you to stay crispy.
Because it wasn't mouthful.
So this is an economic development incident that we have done before for housing projects
done within the city of Miami and its a way for us to partner with those who are doing
the housing project, the way the city can offer something similar to what we do, what we're doing
on the Puma Grant where we're offering some inconseverses to partner with them and make the project
happen.
So what we have, this is the same way waivers that we haven't had in place for other housing
projects that have happened within the community, it's basically a waiver of the...
government fees and any inspection fees but not, doesn't release them from Apple to get all of their permits and have all of their inspections done.
It is a waiver to waive the cost of the roll-offs that we've used if you remember on the Route 66 landing project.
We've made them a roll-off that set their own first during the construction project.
And then it's a waiver of the fees or a partial waiver of the fees for dumping that roll-off.
There's included in there some impact fees.
If there were any those are like if the city has anything in place that requires if you remove a tree you've got to plant a tree
or some things at that nature but that's not really that's not an initiative that these projects.
There will be some minimal electric and water work that different than other housing projects that we've had.
These are new leaders that are set up. These are existing leaders that are already in place.
So there might be some my work or something like that that needs to be done upgraded for these projects.
So is there any other way that the city can give these guys incentives without doing the roll-offs in the tipping fees?
It's taking business away from three local companies in Miami which I personally don't feel right.
It's directly impacted three local companies and we're talking thousands and thousands of dollars.
And then that's thousands and thousands of dollars that the city of Miami is eating.
I get it given them incentives for new businesses coming in.
The Miami housing authority in nine tribes is not a new business coming in.
They have $18 million I got in grants to do all of this stuff.
I feel if the city wants to give them incentives they should find something else that don't take so much money away from the city.
That takes a lot of money away.
Especially a $18 million project and that's a lot of roll-offs.
a lot of waste. I don't think it's right for the city of Miami to take business away from
other local businesses. You give what I'm saying.
Yes, I understand your feedback on that. I think that gives us something to think about
and other creative ways to address those issues.
I realize I got $80 million, but that splits two ways too. Correct, that splits between
my tribes and my members, not just for them. Yes, and there are structural issues with
the myemitowers that are building this located on the name, and so they're looking at ways
right now how to balance this project so that they both, both nine tribes, and myemitowers
still does get a good remodel out of it, because the myemitripes remodel is going to take
more funding than what was originally anticipated due to the structural issues that were.
Just for information, for Simone and my chair, it's not very experienced. Are there hybrid
models of this kind of arrangement? It does seem like when these things come before us.
It's kind of an all or nothing kind of that you're not. Do we ever do some caution?
I think there's lots of different ways for us to approach this. This model that we've got here is just
the precedence that's been said, what we've done in the past, and there's nothing saying that we
we can't veer away from that precedence based on the council's guidance and
and directing, and what they would like to see going forward. So it's all being negotiable, pretty much.
Yes, and this is why we've worked with this group before. This is what we did on the other,
we do this with any of the community action agency, but the houses that they build in our community,
and we did this with the Route 66 landing project. And so that felt like a precedence that was said
and why I structured this the way that it's structured. But of course, open to any feedback and
within what's a better way, or a way that feels better to the council's in the citizen.
and how to structure this.
And still show our support for improved quality of life
for our citizens and my amount of power is being
a quarterstone and our central business district
that's needed help for quite a while.
For those projects you've been to a higher number of times.
No, Route 66 landing was about, it was about 9 million.
Any of the community actually need to see
they build once and then with home at a time.
They have built.
They're working on two right now that will bring them up to eight.
And a community over the last, I'm going to say, four years.
I've built about eight homes on and in and into lots.
We look at what other communities have been for incentives.
And my understanding, it was actually then before I got here
as the city was turning, that it's my understanding.
We chose from what other examples we had,
as to what seemed to fit best for the city of Miami.
And all of them that we've done since I've been here,
have been done off of this model.
It's not to say it began to prove on it or change it.
That's just the way we've done it.
And I hate using those terms.
Right.
I'd like to see something come forward,
even with this project here that is still giving them incentives.
But it's not taking business away from other local businesses.
Well, there's nothing.
I mean, we can, what I would ask is that we think about approving
the waiver of the permit fees,
so that we can go ahead and get the permits issued.
And then we can come back with a amended resolution
that even just has that part in the way that's something that
that sure asks us specifically for it.
What does it cost for room or roll off?
I hate this.
I don't think anyone would know that.
Maybe I'd have to find a picture though.
So I have a, I see my name as prices,
they're on their website right here too.
I can tell you the Route 66 project,
tipping fees that were waived for that project
were about 19,500.
What's this also?
No, no, no.
Just so I have a couple of questions.
Who's, who's doing the work?
So this is,
and HPD is the,
or detect on it, and they much like,
just like what they give us from the 66th
high and local contractors.
OK.
And the process for the government.
They go out to be able.
Right.
So they were hired to put this out as a general bid.
And then it'll be bid.
So help me understand this.
And if I'm asking dumb questions, let me know.
I'm OK with that.
So of course.
So the B-nice.
OK.
You don't have to do this.
So the process for them would be this general contractor
comes in and he's going to do all this work.
And he's got to get rid of this waste in this refuse
in some manner, right?
So would he then reach out to the city,
and then also reach out to the individual businesses
that also do this?
And I'm kind of asking this to delaying in everybody.
Because I'm trying to understand your perspective
and what you're saying by businesses losing money.
So would this be money that the contractors would be paying
to a local rolloff vendor?
Is that what you mean?
Yes.
And so in their process, they likely
we have to go get three bids or would the city just automatically,
because they are doing it for the city,
would the city automatically just get that business?
Because the city also has a business where we do rolloff
rentals in.
Just my question makes sense.
I know what's going on.
So we would wait those fees.
The contractor would contact.
If we weren't waving the fees, is my question.
If it would be on it.
The city wouldn't.
The contractor would call who are they want?
And I mean, they do the work in the city,
for the city that would probably be the first call,
but the city would still be making money off of it.
Right.
But when they call the city, my Emma,
or they call Collins, or my master, or for state rolloff,
I mean, they have four apps that they can choose for.
Right.
But that's just what I'm trying to write my head around is.
If this were done, if we weren't considering waving fees,
the contractors would then have to reach out to local businesses,
but the city wouldn't be involved in that.
Because the city wouldn't been against.
No, the city's prices are set and stone.
What they're price-wise.
Thank you, Githubans, from the other contractors,
and then look at how much it costs at the city and the side.
Who's cheaper than that?
I don't think so.
I understand that.
Thank you.
So, from the city website, there are $300 of mom.
Real.
Right.
And then that's to set it up to the lower it's $35, $385 for the month.
And that's $35 every time you take it to.
So how many, how many do they know?
How many, the estimate of how many times they would have to take that to the...
I don't know.
I have a list of that.
On a project that size, I mean, I've had to, they're looking at 18, 20 plus dumpsters,
on renovating my with ours, or more.
So to finish my question, the reason I asked everything I asked because I was trying to understand
if you give somebody an open check to say you can come and dump whatever you want through
the duration of the project.
Does that increase the amount of tonnage we're going to receive as the city, thereby
taking it to where we spent more money than we even planned on, because if I've got this big
pile of trash that's from my house, I'm just going to bring it to you and give
my point.
Right.
So we talked.
Go ahead.
We talked about that some today, and so first, this project is going to cover two different
seasons for us, because...
Fiscal years.
I'm sorry, fiscal years.
The legal term.
I did seasons fiscal years.
Because our fiscal year ends in June 30th, and then the next one's going to start July
Perth.
So it's going to hit on two different roles for us.
Right.
So I answered your one question.
The other question on is there a limit, or is there...
How's that going to increase our spending for it?
We talked today about, should there be...
Especially since this is going to cover two different budget seasons.
Should there be a limit, like a 20 or 30 or 40 thousand dollar limit on the tipping
side, with the caveat that when we're getting close to that limit, we come back and
talk to the council about where we're at and how much it's cost so far.
I think that's an opportunity for negotiation, as we talked about.
We'll give you X number of pounds.
Everything about it beyond that is your responsibility.
Right.
So maybe that's another creative way of looking at it.
That's that was my reason.
Limit the possibility.
Oh, we sent it to a close to the lawyer.
That sounded good.
So the problem is if we're going to make changes like that, we need to redraft the resolution
but our time constraint problem is that they're waiting right now for us to make a decision
on the permit fees.
And I'm not hearing any discussion about the permit fees.
It would put them behind schedule if we wait till the next meeting.
So what you could...
If nobody has any heartburn about waving the permit fees, we can amend this particular resolution
orally to allow us to go ahead and wave the permit fees and then all the rest of it
come back to you for approval at the next meeting.
I like that.
Please, I like that motion.
Yeah, I make a motion, we do it then set.
I got it all up here.
It's recorded.
And it is, and backed up.
It's like that moment.
He stepped on.
David's.
Hi.
Thank you.
I appreciate it.
11.
Under the business of eight is the business of posting this agenda.
12 trustee, community announcements.
13 adjournments.
12.
Thank you.
Thanks.